<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Digital Caveman. Photoshop retoucher and script/panels developer. I am also an author, check the Courses page!</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 01:23:37 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 01:23:37 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>UXP launch at Adobe MAX 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adobe.com/max.html&quot;&gt;Adobe MAX 2020&lt;/a&gt; conference is unfolding right now, free and online, carrying a number of major updates in the Creative Cloud apps lineup – Photoshop 2021 included. These are three of the major keynote’s highlights IMHO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conan-obrien-mentioning-cep-10-on-stage&quot;&gt;Conan O’Brien mentioning CEP 10 on stage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read that again to sink it in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/Conan.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/Conan.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/Conan@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Conan O'Brien on-stage at MAX 2020&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Conan O'Brien on stage co-hosting MAX 2020. He really said &quot;CEP 10&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adobe-photoshop-2021-supporting-the-new-uxp-plugins-architecture-for-3rd-party-developers&quot;&gt;Adobe Photoshop 2021 supporting the new UXP plugins architecture for 3rd-party developers.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UXP stands for &lt;em&gt;Unified Extensibility Platform&lt;/em&gt;, a technology that was Guinea-pigged on Adobe XD and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/adobetech/announcing-uxp-in-photoshop-288496ab5e3e&quot;&gt;“enables JavaScript-based plugin development with near-native performance”&lt;/a&gt;, quoting Ari Fuchs (Product Lead for in-app extensibility at Adobe).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/UXP.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/UXP.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/UXP@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;The UXP architecture&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The UXP Architecture (don't worry it'll be fine)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My fellow developer, if this doesn’t get you excited feel worried then: &lt;em&gt;in the long run&lt;/em&gt; UXP is going to replace CEP, so you must care sooner or later. Let me stress that it will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; happen overnight, we’re just in the early stages and they’re going to overlap for a significant amount of time. Yet, be aware that UXP is clearly the future of plugins development in Adobe-land for all major CC apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-creative-cloud-marketplace-featuring-uxp-plugins-photoshop&quot;&gt;The Creative Cloud Marketplace featuring UXP plugins Photoshop&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working behind the scenes for months now (“we” being yours truly and other amazing developers, with the invaluable support of Adobe employees) to build and launch our UXP plugins in time for MAX 2020. I’ve released new versions of ALCE, Double USM (that for a limited time are 50% off the original price), and the free utilities Theme Switcher and Floating Adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/UXP-Marketplace.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/UXP-Marketplace.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/UXP-Marketplace@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;The UXP architecture&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The new Plugins panel and the CCD Marketplace &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hub for plugins discovery and installation is now the CCD – Creative Cloud Desktop app – read more on &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.adobe.com/en/2020/10/20/creative-cloud-ecosystem-update-max-2020.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Vijay Vachani, (Sr. Director Product Management &amp;amp; Platform Partnerships at Adobe). Photoshop 2021 also sports a new Plugins menu and panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;uxp-and-you--how-this-blog-can-help-&quot;&gt;UXP and you – how this blog can help 🚀&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, I’ve extensively blogged about CEP in the apparently quite popular “HTML Panels Tip” series. I plan to do the very same here with UXP – with the difference that &lt;strong&gt;I’m also going to record videos&lt;/strong&gt;: the first being an introduction/first-aid to the UXP platform that I’ll release here before the end of the month. So stay tuned! And let me know what you think in the comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, there are a number of freely available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adobe.com/max.html&quot;&gt;Adobe MAX sessions&lt;/a&gt; to watch and learn from – check them out. Stay safe and cheers from Italy! 🖐&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davide&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/development/UXP-at-Adobe-MAX-2020.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/development/UXP-at-Adobe-MAX-2020.html</guid>
        
        <category>UXP</category>
        
        <category>Adobe MAX</category>
        
        
        <category>Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>JavaScript Native Applications for Photoshop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m incredibly happy to announce that my new video-course has been published (confetti falls from the sky). Watch below a 3 minutes short presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8A4UEx8Gb1A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;want-to-know-more&quot;&gt;Want to know more?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve revamped my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ps-scripting.com&quot;&gt;PS-Scripting&lt;/a&gt; website, which is going to be the central hub for all my books and courses, including this new &lt;strong&gt;JavaScript Native Applications for Photoshop&lt;/strong&gt; video-series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center; width:100%&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ps-scripting.com/js-native-apps-for-photoshop.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;box-sizing: border-box; margin: 0; font-family: inherit; overflow: visible; text-transform: none; -webkit-appearance: button; display: inline-block; font-weight: 400; text-align: center; vertical-align: middle; user-select: none; border: 1px solid transparent; transition: color .15s ease-in-out,background-color .15s ease-in-out,border-color .15s ease-in-out,box-shadow .15s ease-in-out; color: #fff; background-color: #673ab7; border-color: #673ab7; padding: .5rem 1rem; font-size: 1.25rem; line-height: 1.5; border-radius: .3rem; margin-top: .25rem; margin-bottom: .25rem; cursor: pointer;&quot;&gt;Visit the course website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To those of you who did express their interest via the contact form: you should have received a special coupon code – check your email. Everyone else: I’ve set an automatic &lt;em&gt;launch price&lt;/em&gt; discount code that is going to expire in the early days of July. Sample content available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thanks&quot;&gt;Thanks!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you all for your support, and for checking this blog from time to time – my friends, 2020 is a tough year! I hope you’re all safe and… reasonably fine? I can’t push that any further giving the crazy times we’re living through. 🖐&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davide&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/development/JavaScript-native-applications-for-photoshop.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/development/JavaScript-native-applications-for-photoshop.html</guid>
        
        <category>Native App</category>
        
        <category>JavaScript</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        
        <category>Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photoshop JS Native Applications Course UPDATE</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;/development/Photoshop-native-applications-wip.html&quot;&gt;you have heard&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve spent the last few months working on my next video-course titled &lt;strong&gt;JavaScript Native Applications for Photoshop&lt;/strong&gt;. The good news is that I am finally done with the recordings! They’ve already been edited, I just need to double-check them one last time and the content will be ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/JSPSApp.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/JSPSApp.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/JSPSApp@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Video Editing&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Bloom (the cat) is not included&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’ll take some extra time, because we’re talking about &lt;strong&gt;28 videos&lt;/strong&gt; for a whopping total of &lt;strong&gt;9 hours&lt;/strong&gt; of Full-HD content, where I am building the app from the ground up, i.e. starting with an empty folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also need to create thumbnails, marketing assets and the like (the part I admittedly enjoy the less). Keep an eye to this blog for the official release announcement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/list.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/list.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2020/05/list@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Video thumbnails&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Video list (wip)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pricing-and-availability&quot;&gt;Pricing and Availability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full price is going to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$149&lt;/strong&gt; for individuals, with lifetime updates and HD videos for streaming.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$249&lt;/strong&gt; for enterprise licenses up to 10 seats, with lifetime updates and HD videos for download.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fill the form below if you’re interested in receiving an early bird discounted offer before the course goes public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;540&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; src=&quot;https://3dc77a80.sibforms.com/serve/MUIEAHsKpwIq1yNWbj_lxLqna87ra1XJHISVSYzDNKhSsYsYb4rLHME8ojWOr2YC4crxEuI6GRaX1pYUKI5bLh6Knr5sKmIwW1kvScZISpzmqLc1EUaREv-6OVq9ff5bRhJEKnM4Qi-2WIBNuk1Q4IlyEGw5jxOj1iiVa3KqHUw8x2V0NyAwNEZec3NIfkETDoIDPbaN-DPhUG86&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;auto&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;display: block;margin-left: auto;margin-right: auto;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/development/Photoshop-native-applications-update.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/development/Photoshop-native-applications-update.html</guid>
        
        <category>Native App</category>
        
        <category>JavaScript</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        
        <category>Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photoshop JS Native Applications Course (work-in-progress)</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am working on a new series of &lt;strong&gt;video-tutorials&lt;/strong&gt; on Photoshop Development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The subject is going to be &lt;strong&gt;Native Applications&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.app&lt;/code&gt; for Mac and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt; for Windows, entirely written in Javascript) that connect to Photoshop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think CEP (aka HTML) Panels, but transplanted outside Photoshop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Demo App is 98% complete: for fun, it also implements a simple &lt;em&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/em&gt; pre-trained model for image classification.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Availability&lt;/strong&gt;: approx. Q3/2020, updates in the blog.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pricing&lt;/strong&gt;: $149 for individuals, $249 for companies; early bird discounts available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-time-no-see&quot;&gt;Long time no see&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve slowed down a bit with blog-posting in the last year due to a mix of personal reasons (burnout recovery, house restoration, work, fighting with a neighbour-from-hell, this kind of stuff) plus a general lack of relevant things to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, since late Q2/2019 I’ve been playing with the idea of building independent, native apps that can connect to Photoshop and act very much like CEP Panels would. As I’m slooooow and distracted, I’ve got to the point of having a working Demo App in my hands around March 2020 – not bad for a coding-sloth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-native-apps&quot;&gt;Why Native Apps?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a bit tired of CEP: I wanted to allow myself the luxury of &lt;em&gt;some more control&lt;/em&gt; over the development environment; if you’re a CEP developer I think you can relate. As anybody who’s been around in this business long enough knows, we’ve had the possibility to connect to PS &lt;em&gt;from the outside&lt;/em&gt; for like 10 years (now you can call me a true sloth); reliable Native apps with JavaScript are here, so it was a no-brainer for me to give it a try, finally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pros&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You’re &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; in charge over the technologies to use – no more “This has been fixed in PS 2029, but older PS versions are still out-of-luck”, or the cyclic “you’ve been doing X for a jolly bunch of years, guess what from now on it’s done the Y way” kind of troubles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Still JS/Node.js stuff, easy transition if you come from a CEP background.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can update to Chromium/Node-latest whenever you want for whatever PS version you want.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Native means independent, separate, dock-bouncing apps, with access to OS-level stuff like tray icons, notifications, FileSystem, you name it; Mac and Windows alike.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not all projects are a good fit for an independent app: if you need a tighter, super-fast integration with PS, stick to CEP or whatever &lt;em&gt;default&lt;/em&gt; technology Adobe provides.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s a bit of a learning curve, but I’m here to ease the process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-it-work-technically-speaking&quot;&gt;How does it work, technically speaking?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NW.js, Vue.js, Vuex, Socket.io, Adobe Generator Plugin, MobileNet, Node.js stuff, trial and error. For now you’ll make do with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-will-the-video-course-cover&quot;&gt;What will the Video Course cover?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to build a demo app from scratch over the course of some hours of recording. Features are totally arbitrary, and it have been chosen to serve just one purpose: showing how things can be done in the context of a native app connecting to PS, i.e. solving specific problems that you’re likely to run into (e.g. passing data from/to PS, executing scripts, synchronous/asynchronous operations, storing permanent data between sessions, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/demo-app.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does the demo app do?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the user selects a bunch of files from the disk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the user also toggles few Image Classification tags&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the app retrieves ActionSets/Actions loaded in Photoshop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if each file’s &lt;em&gt;subject&lt;/em&gt; matches the ones selected by the user (that one document actually &lt;em&gt;depicts&lt;/em&gt; a tiger), Photoshop will process it with the selected Action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when the batch ends, a System Notification pops up some info&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As simple as it looks, it’s enough to build a rather structured NW.js/Vue.js architecture that can serve as a blueprint for more complex projects of yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything’s based on a solid build system, so 99% of the tasks are completely automated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;courses-goals&quot;&gt;Course’s goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ps-scripting.com/bundles.html&quot;&gt;everything&lt;/a&gt; I’ve ever published, the main goal is to give you a substantial head-start, and save you all the time I’ve spent stuck trying to solve specific technical problems. As in life, there are many more ways to mess up than to get it right: this course will provide you with a selected range of working options to build commercial-grade applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pricing-and-availability&quot;&gt;Pricing and Availability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m bugfixing the app, which functionally speaking is done. Knowing myself, it will take me some more months to record the actual content, so friendly advice: don’t hold your breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’ll be priced according to previous courses of mine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$149&lt;/strong&gt; for individuals, with lifetime updates and HD videos for streaming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$249&lt;/strong&gt; for enterprise licenses up to 10 seats, with lifetime updates and HD videos for download&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early bird discounts available. If you’re interested, please enter your email in the form below (no spam at all); you’ll receive a notification with a discounted offer before the course goes public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;540&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; src=&quot;https://3dc77a80.sibforms.com/serve/MUIEAHsKpwIq1yNWbj_lxLqna87ra1XJHISVSYzDNKhSsYsYb4rLHME8ojWOr2YC4crxEuI6GRaX1pYUKI5bLh6Knr5sKmIwW1kvScZISpzmqLc1EUaREv-6OVq9ff5bRhJEKnM4Qi-2WIBNuk1Q4IlyEGw5jxOj1iiVa3KqHUw8x2V0NyAwNEZec3NIfkETDoIDPbaN-DPhUG86&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;auto&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;display: block;margin-left: auto;margin-right: auto;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless they’re along the lines of &lt;em&gt;“Sir, why X instead of Y?”&lt;/em&gt;, I encourage you to post in the comments below. Thanks for reading and have a good day!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/development/Photoshop-native-applications-wip.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/development/Photoshop-native-applications-wip.html</guid>
        
        <category>Native App</category>
        
        <category>JavaScript</category>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        
        <category>Development</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The state of Hasselblad Flextight scanners, FlexColor and the 3F format</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In case you missed it, Flextight scanners have vanished from the Hasselblad website around May 2019 and macOS Catalina doesn’t run FlexColor anymore. No software updates are planned, plus I’ve run into problems dealing with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fff&lt;/code&gt; files in Photoshop 2020. Heavens!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flextight-scanners&quot;&gt;Flextight scanners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flextight X1 and X5, the flagship (and only left) models in Hasselblad’s lineup have been discontinued: EOL, kaputt. No official announcement has been published, but a number of users around the world have had the news confirmed either from dealers or servicing shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pointless to ask the reason why, scanners have always been a low priority asset to Hasselblad. Flextight know-how and hardware were acquired in 2014 when the company merged with Imacon: reliable sources told me that the engineering team has always been quite small. My best bet is that the 2017 acquisition of Hasselblad by DJI, a Chinese drone-making company, gave scanners the &lt;em&gt;coup de grace&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that servicing will be available for the foreseeable future, as customer service wrote me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Flextight scanners are full service supported in our factory service in Gothenburg, Sweden and a selected number of regional scanner partners are able to perform local service and preventive maintenance. We will continue to perform service for these scanners as long as we will have spare parts, therefore it is difficult to appreciate for how long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this is what you can read when logging in the private area of the Hasselblad website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/servicing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flexcolor-software&quot;&gt;FlexColor software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unclear information has been given to users in the past, when many of us pinged Hasselblad about the pressing issue of macOS 10.15 Catalina blocking 32bit applications. Any hope to see a 64bit FlexColor rewrite has been definitely flushed away when customer support eventually started to reply that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] we currently have no plans to release an updated version of Flexcolor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, the software has been EOLed very much like the hardware. Not that it has ever received much care: the last available versions are 4.8.13 (2011, for Mac) and 4.8.9 (2012, for Windows).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/fc-error.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 357px; height: 180px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the best of my knowledge, the Windows version still runs on whatever version is Windows at now, but with macOS you’re capped to 10.14 Mojave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither FlexColor nor the scanners do require a high-performance computer, they’re probably going to work fine with old dedicated hardware for years to come. I think it’s possible to run Catalina and virtualize (with Parallels or VMWare) Mojave so that you can still run 32bit apps. Let’s hope that by the time the whole process becomes impractical or the spare parts are out of stock, the film we want to scan has been eroded away by chemical remains and fungi – checkmate, problem solved&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1980&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1980&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, due to legal reasons (very likely the use of some internal libraries that prevent it) FlexColor can’t be open-sourced. There are rumors about VueScan willing (or having been asked) to implement a module that would drive the Flextight hardware, but I couldn’t been able to find any official statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the state of affairs for the hardware, what about existing archives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3f-files&quot;&gt;3F files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here things are getting slightly more complex, please bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we all know, FlexColor is used by archivists and photoshoppers alike to browse through, and extract &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tif&lt;/code&gt; files from, huge collections of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.fff&lt;/code&gt; (aka 3F) files. You may or may not know that the 3F format is nothing but a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tif&lt;/code&gt; file with some proprietary tags: to prove it, try renaming a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.fff&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tif&lt;/code&gt; and open it in Photoshop. The extra stuff is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the compressed/low-res bitmap preview that FlexColor uses to &lt;em&gt;temporarily&lt;/em&gt; display the 3F while waiting to read the actual data from the file (only if the 3F isn’t too large, in which case you’re &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; only shown the preview)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;metadata related to the scan acquisition and FlexColor settings (e.g. curves, FlexTouch, saturation, snapshots, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have grown accustomed to skip FlexColor altogether for anything but driving the scanner (acquiring the 3F), and browsing (i.e. visualizing the files). That is to say: I &lt;strong&gt;do not use FlexColor anymore for any 3F processing&lt;/strong&gt; nor &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tif&lt;/code&gt; extraction. I’ve never liked FlexColor rudimental, limited features – they were sort-of OK in the mid-2000s, or for large files batches quick post-processing. My client’s work today is more focused on a smaller selection of scans, to be post-produced very accurately, so I only use Photoshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To briefly sum up the way I use to work&lt;/strong&gt; (which I can expand in a separate blogpost – leave a comment below in case it is of any interest):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I open the 3F in Photoshop (thanks to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Imacon3F.plugin&lt;/code&gt; or its &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.8bf&lt;/code&gt; Windows version), which in my case is going to appear as a color negative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I apply an Invert adjustment layer and a couple of Curves adjustment layers to make it look more or less &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; to my eyes – no need to be precise here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I duplicate the background layer and perform all sorts of retouching voodoo (against dust, scratches, chemicals stains, fingerprints, semen, etc.), saving this intermediate layered file as a separate, temporary &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.psb&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When I’m happy, I flatten all the bitmap layers and discard all the adjustment layers, so that I’m back with a one-layer, color negative file again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I re-open the original &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.fff&lt;/code&gt; file, drag and drop the retouched layer from the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.psb&lt;/code&gt;, flatten, and save as &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.CLEAN.fff&lt;/code&gt; – this because one never knows what the future brings… I then trash the intermediate &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.psb&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I keep the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.CLEAN.fff&lt;/code&gt; open: assign the &lt;em&gt;FlexColor Input&lt;/em&gt; ICC, convert to Adobe RGB, Invert, and save my working file as a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.psb&lt;/code&gt;. This is my starting point, to which I apply the usual Curves, and whatever it takes to make the image work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter another stray bullet in the Hasselblad game: Adobe. It turns out that &lt;strong&gt;Photoshop 2020 doesn’t want to open 3Fs anymore&lt;/strong&gt;, popping up this new errors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/ps-error.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image proportion has changed the imacon 3f plugin can't save the file&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent versions, you already had to set the Open dialog’s settings to &lt;em&gt;Enable: All Documents&lt;/em&gt; (and of course the &lt;em&gt;Format: Imacon 3f&lt;/em&gt;) otherwise Adobe Camera Raw kicked in trying to open the file, mistaking it as coming from a digital back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last working version (at least on a Mac) is Photoshop CC 2019 – which is a &lt;strong&gt;big concern&lt;/strong&gt;. Why? You may or may not have heard that in the last months Adobe has aggressively restricted the licensed versions range for Photoshop – e.g. you cannot, theoretically, install or run, say, Photoshop CC 2015 anymore. Without entering into yet another rabbit hole, it all boils down to royalties with third-parties, very likely Dolby&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:dolby&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:dolby&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, Adobe’s versions policy is (and it is fair to expect that it will be their default from now on) to license N-1 versions – in other words: you’ll be allowed to download and install the latest Photoshop, plus the version before it, period. At the time I’m writing this, it is PS 2020 + PS CC 2019. In one year, CC 2019 will be dropped, and it’ll be PS 2021 + PS 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means: one year from now, the &lt;em&gt;officially available&lt;/em&gt; Photoshop versions won’t open 3F files anymore, and working versions’ installers won’t be available for download either. LMAO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the tangentially related problem of macOS notarization/digital signature, from macOS Catalina onwards: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.plugin&lt;/code&gt; files are requested to be at least&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:sign&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:sign&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; signed by the developer, otherwise macOS GateKeeper will prevent to run them. This is not too much of a big deal, I have an active Apple Developer membership and I can sign the file myself if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hasselblad Flextight X1 and X5 scanners (previously known as Imacon) are discontinued. Scanner servicing will be provided as usual &lt;em&gt;as long as spare parts will be available&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FlexColor is abandonware: it doesn’t run on any macOS &amp;gt; 10.14.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3F files don’t open anymore in Photoshop 2020; very likely the CC 2019 installer is not going to be available one year from now, and even if you have one, it’s definitely possible that macOS Catalina will prevent &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Imacon3F.plugin&lt;/code&gt; from working because it’s not signed/notarized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workarounds-if-any&quot;&gt;Workarounds (if any)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is partly subjective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acquiring new scans&lt;/strong&gt;, for the time being, requires FlexColor; so either you keep dedicated hardware running macOS Mojave, or you switch to Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Browsing 3F collections&lt;/strong&gt; is, and will keep being, a pain in the butt: FlexColor is the &lt;em&gt;lesser evil&lt;/em&gt;, Adobe Bridge seems unable to load just the low-res preview that is embedded in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.fff&lt;/code&gt; files and it takes forever to read the file content to create a thumbnail. The same holds true with Finder. I’m not aware of any other viable options for the Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extracting &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.tif&lt;/code&gt; files for &lt;strong&gt;3F post-processing&lt;/strong&gt; is not a problem, as long as the Photoshop plugin keeps working 🤞🏻.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to comment below if you have updated news, workflow suggestions, or you just want to share your point of view as a Hasselblad user.
  Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1980&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Please bear with me but I’m right in the middle of the postproduction of a batch of large format, color negative scans from the early 1980, and it’s a mess. Are you nostalgic of the old days of analogic photography? Bloody hell, no. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1980&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:dolby&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plagiarismtoday.com/2019/05/15/adobe-dolby-and-the-battle-over-your-software/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more info about the Adobe-Dolby lawsuit. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:dolby&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:sign&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It is unclear to me, at the moment, whether a digital signature is enough or I would be required to notarize the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.plugin&lt;/code&gt; as well – not a big deal either, but not running Catalina myself I cannot test it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:sign&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/2019-12-07/2019-12-07-hasselblad-flextight-flexcolor-3f/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/12/2019-12-07/2019-12-07-hasselblad-flextight-flexcolor-3f/</guid>
        
        <category>Hasselblad</category>
        
        <category>Imacon</category>
        
        <category>Flextight</category>
        
        <category>FlexColor</category>
        
        <category>3F</category>
        
        
        <category>Photoshop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Leanpub alternatives, IMHO</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re into technical writing, read along. I’ve used Leanpub’s services for two books of mine out of three, and I am still 100% sure that I couldn’t make a better choice. But when you’re more experienced, there might be reasons to look for alternatives: I’ll tell you mine, how I’ve sorted my doubts out, and what I’ve eventually chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notable options among others are &lt;a href=&quot;https://pandoc.org/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.softcover.io/&quot;&gt;SoftCover&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latex-project.org/&quot;&gt;LaTeX&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://affinity.serif.com/en-gb/publisher/&quot;&gt;Affinity Publisher&lt;/a&gt;. Read along to see the piece of technology that I’ve embraced, and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-own-needs-which-may-differ-from-yours&quot;&gt;My own needs (which may differ from yours)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am into technical publishing/programming books: I’ve written three of them, that I refer to as &lt;em&gt;“the two big ones”&lt;/em&gt; (more than 350 pages, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.htmlpanelsbook.com/&quot;&gt;Adobe Photoshop HTML Panels Development&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ps-scripting.com&quot;&gt;Professional Photoshop Scripting&lt;/a&gt;), and &lt;em&gt;“the short one”&lt;/em&gt; (less than 100 pages, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidebarranca.com/2018/01/ultimate-guide-native-installers-automated-build-system/&quot;&gt;The Ultimate Guide to Native Installers and Automated Build Systems&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ps-scripting.com/bundles.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/books.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/books.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/books@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;My Books&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do sell them on my own via &lt;a href=&quot;https://gumroad.com/&quot;&gt;Gumroad&lt;/a&gt;; I do the marketing/newsletter on my own; I find beta readers/tech editors on my own; I do design the book on my own. Basically, I’m ever such a grumpy, control-freak guy with some tech background who needs to produce the best looking &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; that he can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuff &lt;strong&gt;I very much like&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being able to customize the page design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relying on a repeatable, robust process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open source / offline tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automated typesetting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuff &lt;strong&gt;I don’t particularly need/like&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anything that goes beyond the PDF creation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Online tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To some extent, I can trade easiness for customizability because I do not write regularly: I embarque on big projects about once every couple of years, I am not willing to reinvent the wheel each time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is my personal quest for viable Leanpub alternatives: it is 100% based on my needs, skillset and amount of time I can currently devote on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-am-i-looking-for-alternatives-in-the-first-place&quot;&gt;Why am I looking for alternatives in the first place?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, &lt;strong&gt;Leanpub is by far the most usable, well crafted service on the market for ebook authors, and I couldn’t recommend them more&lt;/strong&gt;. My &lt;em&gt;two big books&lt;/em&gt; have been produced by Leanpub, and could I go back in time I’d choose them again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/PSScripting.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/PSScripting.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/PSScripting@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Professional Photoshop Scripting, a Leanpub book&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Professional Photoshop Scripting, a Leanpub book&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only they provide you with great tools for creating e-books, connecting authors with readers, managing sales, landing pages and the like, they are also heavily involved into advancing the industry with new standards such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com/markua/read&quot;&gt;Markua&lt;/a&gt; (a book-targeted, enhanced flavour of MarkDown). Lately, they have broaden their offer developing courses creation tools as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re tackling your first book, then Leanpub is a no brainer. Stop reading this and go creating a new Author account on their website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the show stopper for me is that the PDF creation is a &lt;strong&gt;remote process&lt;/strong&gt; – well managed, sync’d with Dropbox, hooked with GitHub/Bitbuckets, yet remote nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/generation.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/generation.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/generation@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Leanpub remote PDF generation&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leanpub remote PDF generation&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t necessarily would like WYSIWYG, but synch’ing, waiting some minutes for the generation, and downloading is adding a friction that over time I’ve found unbearable. Especially when something doesn’t go the way you expect, i.e. if the layout requires many small tweaks, or worse the PDF generation crashes due to errors that aren’t easy to debug. When needed, Leanpub support never fails you; still, you need them to look at the log and find out what went wrong. Interrupting the creative flow is never a jolly business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Features wise, I have little to complain: some of the limitations I had when I wrote my &lt;em&gt;two big books&lt;/em&gt; with Leanpub may have been overcome with the introduction of Markua, which wasn’t ready back then. Extra customization is always welcome, but the built-in set is comprehensive enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-leanpub-pdf-generation&quot;&gt;The Leanpub PDF generation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically speaking, at least with the MarkDown-in, PDF-out process, Leanpub relies on an intermediate LaTeX step; so it actually is MD to LaTeX to PDF (I suppose it is the same with Markua, but I can’t be sure). If you’re not familiar with it, LaTeX is a &lt;em&gt;“document preparation system for high-quality typesetting”&lt;/em&gt; – or in layman terms, an horribly complex markup language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;MarkDown is a markup language too, but much simpler. It lets you write &lt;em&gt;plain text&lt;/em&gt; with a very light and minimal markup so that titles are made with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; symbols, the asterisks in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;**that**&lt;/code&gt; turn &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt; bold, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/markdown.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/markdown.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/markdown@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;MarkDown Example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A MarkDown example (this blogpost)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, you might simplify matters saying that, among the rest, Leanpub has put together a very well designed set of &lt;em&gt;LaTeX styles&lt;/em&gt; on top of a well-crafted MD conversion, so that the resulting PDF is remarkably good (setting aside &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.epub&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.mobi&lt;/code&gt; versions, that are not a strict requirement for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leanpubs-pros-and-cons&quot;&gt;Leanpub’s Pros and Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMHO, on the plus side: writing in MarkDown is almost frictionless, the MD to PDF workflow frees your mind and lets you concentrate on producing the actual content, Markua is a promising evolution, they offer a ton of marketing features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMHO, the cons: there is a limited set of available customizations, it’s a paid service (as it should be!), above all the PDF generation doesn’t happen locally but on their servers – which is the real obstacle for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-have-evaluated-alternatives&quot;&gt;How I have evaluated alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not the kind of guy who would write a book using Libre Office, and exporting it to PDF right away. It may be super handy for articles, yet I don’t think it is up to the task for books. Or possibly it is, but either I am not familiar enough with it to deal with named cross-references, etc. or it is not a good fit for &lt;em&gt;programming&lt;/em&gt; books: e.g., my stuff involves a good deal of listings (programming code, mostly but not exclusively written in JavaScript) that require to be numbered and colored with proper syntax-highlighting, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tradeoff that I can bear: giving up some of the easiness that comes with writing-in-MarkDown-and-forget-about-everything-else. I.e., I am ready to decouple the writing from the typesetting processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pandoc&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandoc.org/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; is an open source set of tools that let you convert between formats - a lot of them, including MarkDown,  ePub, Microsoft Word, InDesign &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.idml&lt;/code&gt;, PDF (via LaTeX). If you need it, you can get get a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.mobi&lt;/code&gt; from an &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.epub&lt;/code&gt; with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;https://calibre-ebook.com/&quot;&gt;Calibre&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pandoc is super-awesome, it is free, it runs as a command-line utility from the Terminal for Mac, Win and Linux, it provides the same sort of MD to LaTeX to PDF workflow that Leanpub sports. There’s an elephant in the room, though: you must rely on a set of custom &lt;em&gt;LaTeX styles&lt;/em&gt; to tweak the PDF appearance. In other words, the default conversion is elegant as almost any LaTeX document is by default, but rather dull: if you want to use some of the fancier stuff and you don’t know your LaTeX… you’re &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; out of luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there is plenty of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jgm/pandoc/wiki/User-contributed-templates&quot;&gt;templates&lt;/a&gt;. I did play a little bit with one called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Wandmalfarbe/pandoc-latex-template&quot;&gt;Eisvogel&lt;/a&gt;, but I couldn’t really figure out how to bend it to my needs, nor I did know how to “teach Pandoc” to interpret the MarkDown that I would like to be linked, say, to a custom LaTeX &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\newcommand&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/eisvogel.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/eisvogel.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/eisvogel@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;The Eisvogel LaTeX template for Pandoc&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Eisvogel LaTeX template for Pandoc&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I was facing two distinct and quite steep learning curves: getting the hang of LaTeX and Pandoc &lt;em&gt;at the same time&lt;/em&gt;, I got frightened and called quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;softcover&quot;&gt;Softcover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.softcover.io/&quot;&gt;SoftCover&lt;/a&gt; for my &lt;em&gt;short book&lt;/em&gt; a while ago, and I was quite pleased. Keeping it to the book generation process alone (Softcover offer sales services too), it is based on an open-source Ruby command-line set of tools to process MarkDown in, and output PDF, plus &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.epub&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.mobi&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Softcover is more explicit in terms of intermediate steps, for it advocates the use of PolyTeX: &lt;em&gt;“a strict subset of the LaTeX typesetting language”&lt;/em&gt;. Quite interestingly, you’re allowed to mix-in some LaTeX in the MarkDown, that works in combination with the Softcover provided styles. The more LaTeX you know, the better you can customize them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/softcover.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/softcover.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/softcover@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;The Softcover Manual&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Softcover Manual&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, my experience with Softcover on the first book was OK. I had to tweak quite some things in the styles to my taste, and I’ve copied and pasted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://tex.stackexchange.com&quot;&gt;TeX StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; more than a sensible developer would find appropriate – without really knowing what I was doing. Still, I did like more the design that comes with Leanpub out-of-the-box; on the plus side, I enjoyed very much the local PDF generation and PolyTeX features such as named cross-references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since I’ve mentioned them a couple of times already, a &lt;em&gt;named cross reference&lt;/em&gt; is a piece of text (could be a title, a listing, a table, etc.) to which you attach a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\label&lt;/code&gt;, and to which you can refer to with the same label. Magic happens because you automatically get both the correct numeration and name (here, “figure 1.2”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cref.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cref.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/cref@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Named cross references&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Named cross references&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, when I got back to my one year old &lt;em&gt;short book&lt;/em&gt; markdown text to add some new content, the book generation failed. I couldn’t get to the root of the problem in a decent amount of time – a Ruby version issue, some dependencies missing, who knows. That mishap did leave me with a vague “lack of robustness” feeling: had I used Softcover more frequently, I would have been able to steer the wheel and correct any small issue that, inevitably, presented itself over time. But after such a long hiatus, I felt that using a tool on which I wasn’t in full control was too much of a gamble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;affinity-publisher&quot;&gt;Affinity Publisher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a true believer on &lt;a href=&quot;https://affinity.serif.com&quot;&gt;Affinity&lt;/a&gt;’s products lineup, so I’ve listed their Publisher instead of Adobe InDesign – even if I’m more familiar with the latter than the former&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:publisher&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:publisher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. That is to say that I have evaluated the possibility to build the book “manually”, with a page design application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must confess that, even if I would have enjoyed the possibility to get a live, visual feedback and pixel precision positioning, I tend to keep InDesign and its breed at an arm distance whenever possible (which, thanks to my job, is not always): I’m afraid I just don’t like it. The idea to compose a short book, not to mention a long one, sounds dreadful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/publisher.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/publisher.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/publisher@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Affinity Publisher&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Affinity Publisher&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides, listings are not so easy to typeset on Publisher: you’d need to copy the code from, say, Visual Studio Code, paste it on Pages/Word, copy it again and eventually paste inside a Text Frame to retain the RTF information – i.e. to keep the Syntax Highlighting. Which is a PITA for code maintenance and it doesn’t really scale up when the book grows. I’ve logged a feature request for automated programming languages syntax highlighting on Affinity’s forums, and I’ve moved on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;LaTeX&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, the idea of messing with master pages, character and paragraph styles, references, etc. on a page design application such as Affinity Publisher shedded a new, much brighter light on LaTeX. Which I started exploring. Given that I tend to fall in love with whatever piece of technology that you put in front of my nose, I tried to be unbiased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LaTeX is mostly used in academia, almost exclusively sciences and maths. It is known for providing an elegant typesetting out of the box, and equations so &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-01796-1&quot;&gt;beautifully drawn&lt;/a&gt; that mathematicians could stare at them for hours on end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/math.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/math.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/math@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;LaTeX equations example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;LaTeX equations example&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it seems to have spread just because academic writers were such bad typesetters that they desperately needed some sort of tool that let them focus on the content only. That said, it strikes me that among the many hundreds of packages (i.e. add-on features) available for LaTeX, their documentation, that is obviously written in LaTeX, kind of stinks. Visually I mean, it’s ugly – which is quite ironic I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LaTeX is unfriendly to say the least: the learning curve is undoubtedly &lt;em&gt;steep&lt;/em&gt;. For some reason, it seems like documentation is chiefly reference-based, with rare occasional examples. You can easily find yourself browsing for 7 years old replies on TeX StackExchange thinking: “Sweet, that is probably gonna work” (would it be a JavaScript library, a 7 months old reply has already a good chance to be outdated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I subscribe 100% to the author of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.danielallington.net/2016/09/the-latex-fetish/&quot;&gt;The LaTeX Fetish (Or: Don’t write in LaTeX! It’s just for typesetting)&lt;/a&gt;, which has an interesting series of comments and replies. I could never write on LaTeX: it is too crowded, MarkDown is much less distracting to the eye. But I agree that LaTeX, a fossil from the past, still rocks as a typesetting tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I thought: if Pandoc, Softcover, and Leanpub are all LaTeX based; if I seem unable to just hack my way through them; wouldn’t it be better if I started with the real thing from scratch? And so I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-latex-journey&quot;&gt;My LaTeX journey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I’ve set a simple goal: re-typeset the &lt;em&gt;small book&lt;/em&gt;, that you may remember was built with Softcover so I had both the MarkDown and the PolyTeX code available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to try LaTeX, head &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latex-project.org/get/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and download the distribution for Mac, Win or Linux. Speaking of applications (IDEs), there are freewares such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://texstudio.org/&quot;&gt;TeXstudio&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.uoregon.edu/koch/texshop/&quot;&gt;TeXShop&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve found more user-friendly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.texpad.com/&quot;&gt;Texpad&lt;/a&gt; (30$), or the free Visual Studio Code extension &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/James-Yu/LaTeX-Workshop&quot;&gt;LaTeX Workshop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/texpad.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/texpad.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/texpad@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;The TexPad app, with almost-live preview&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The TexPad app, with almost-live preview&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve started reading documentation and books: there are so many LaTeX Fetishists that manuals are abundant. In my experience, it is far better to start from a blank style (a file with a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.sty&lt;/code&gt; extension) and add pieces one by one, learning what they do as you insert them, instead of borrowing a complete style from somebody else and hack it to your taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Line after line, I’ve merged pieces from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Softcover.sty&lt;/code&gt;,  &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Eisvogel.sty&lt;/code&gt; and stuff I’ve found online; apparently there is a package for everything, from footnotes to listings, quotes, colors, bookmarks, you name it&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:packages&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:packages&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It would be impossible to list them all here – the bottom-line is that creating a decent set of styles for a book that is at least up to Leanpub standards is in fact a doable task for anyone with some inclination to code tinkering. Dare I to say, I’ve even got better listings 😉&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/listings.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/10/listings.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/10/listings@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Custom styled listings&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Custom styled listings in LaTeX with the `listings` package&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I cannot call myself a LaTeX expert at all, but for sure a better hacker: at least I am able to understand what is in the realm of my possibilities and what’s better to keep away from. I’ve succeeded in re-typesetting my &lt;em&gt;short book&lt;/em&gt; in two/three night-time weeks, for which I’m quite pleased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-only-time-will-tell&quot;&gt;What only time will tell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is to be seen whether I will perceive LaTeX as a robust solution, i.e. will the same source, untouched, compile flawlessly one year from now, on a different machine? I have the feeling that such is the case, unless my cat sits on the keyboard when I’m off the desk. LaTeX is just markup after all, and it is so modular that I doubt it will all crash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I am slightly more acquainted with it, I may want to approach Pandoc again. No doubts that, as I’ve mentioned before, LaTeX isn’t a tool for writing but typesetting: I still miss the MarkDown to PDF workflow. If I can manage to create a template for Pandoc that takes into account all my listings styles and the like, I’ll be the happiest camper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it has already happened countless times to me, learning is rarely a direct path from point A to point B. I still have to find my dream workflow, but I think the one I’ve used – unless proven otherwise – is viable to say the least, and a good fit to the requirements I’ve set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a technical writer feel free to comment below, I’m eager to listen to your experience. Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:publisher&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Let’s not forget that, to date, Affinity isn’t Subscription based; and it has never told its users they can get sued for using old versions, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/a3xk3p/adobe-tells-users-they-can-get-sued-for-using-old-versions-of-photoshop&quot;&gt;like Adobe&lt;/a&gt;… &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:publisher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:packages&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My understanding is that LaTeX is a macro-language on top of TeX, which is way too complex to be used right away. In addition to what comes built-in with LaTeX itself, you’re usually advised to load &lt;em&gt;packages&lt;/em&gt;: users contributed “macros” that make the process of implementing new features much easier. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:packages&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/2019-10-15-leanpub-alternatives-IMHO/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/10/2019-10-15-leanpub-alternatives-IMHO/</guid>
        
        <category>Leanpub</category>
        
        <category>Softcover</category>
        
        <category>Pandoc</category>
        
        <category>LaTeX</category>
        
        
        <category>Digital Publishing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notarizing installers for macOS Catalina</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[See newest updates at the bottom of the article]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Apple (read &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/documentation/security/notarizing_your_app_before_distribution&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; the whole article):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Apple notary service is an automated system that scans your software for malicious content, checks for code-signing issues, and returns the results to you quickly. Notarization gives users more confidence that the Developer ID-signed software you distribute has been checked by Apple for malicious components. Notarization is not App Review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it is some kind of whitelisting. From macOS Catalina on (late September 2019), &lt;strong&gt;notarization is mandatory&lt;/strong&gt;: your installers won’t work if you don’t do your homeworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gatekeeper&quot;&gt;Gatekeeper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your customers run your product’s &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;installer.pkg&lt;/code&gt;, macOS Gatekeeper connects with Apple, checking whether the file you’re executing has been vetted and thus can be run safely. If this is the case, Gatekeeper pops up the usual warning anyway:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/gatekeeper.gif&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/gatekeeper.gif 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/05/gatekeeper@2x.gif 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Book Design&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because users can also be offline, you can &lt;em&gt;staple&lt;/em&gt; the notary service’s response ticket directly to the installer – an optional but recommended step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-need&quot;&gt;What you need&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An active subscription to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/&quot;&gt;Apple Developer Program&lt;/a&gt; ($99 per year).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Xcode 10 or newer (free download via the App Store).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An app-specific password defined for your AppleID (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT204397&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for instruction).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notarization-walkthrough&quot;&gt;Notarization walkthrough&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume that you are at least vaguely familiar with the topic of code signing. I’m going to show you how to notarize a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pkg&lt;/code&gt; installer; caveats for slightly more complex scenarios (e.g. a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.dmg&lt;/code&gt; that wraps a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pkg&lt;/code&gt; and/or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.app&lt;/code&gt; plus other assets) will follow in a later section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-create-a-developerid-installer-certificate&quot;&gt;1. Create a DeveloperID Installer certificate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Log in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com&quot;&gt;Apple Developer portal&lt;/a&gt; portal and follow the “Certificates, Identifiers &amp;amp; Profiles” section. Create a new Certificate: when asked, select DeveloperID Installer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/DeveloperID.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/DeveloperID.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/05/DeveloperID@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Book Design&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the instruction to complete the process – you’ll be required to open the Certificate Assistant from the Keychain Access application to create a Certificate request, then upload it to the Developer Portal. When the process is complete, you’ll be presented with a download link for your certificate, to be imported via double click into the Keychain Access app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can verify that the certificate has been successfully installed opening the Terminal and pasting the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;security find-identity -v

1) 6A7C3D1A28FA5483E5E8857F2A12EDC71731CAED &quot;Developer ID Installer: Davide Barranca (I2WD7PWGD9)&quot;
  1 valid identities found
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep note of the string between quotes that says &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;Developer ID Installer: ...&quot;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-signing-the-installer&quot;&gt;2. Signing the Installer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t just need to &lt;em&gt;notarize&lt;/em&gt; an installer, it must be &lt;em&gt;signed&lt;/em&gt; first. Assuming that the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;installer.pkg&lt;/code&gt; file sits in the folder you have &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; to in the Terminal window, you &lt;strong&gt;sign the installer&lt;/strong&gt; with the following command (the output I’ve got comes right below the first line):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;productsign --sign &quot;Developer ID Installer: Davide Barranca&quot; ./installer.pkg ./installer_signed.pkg

  productsign: using timestamp authority for signature
  productsign: signing product with identity &quot;Developer ID Installer: Davide Barranca (I2WD7PWGD9)&quot; from keychain /Library/Keychains/System.keychain
  productsign: adding certificate &quot;Developer ID Certification Authority&quot;
  productsign: adding certificate &quot;Apple Root CA&quot;
  productsign: Wrote signed product archive to ./installer_signed.pkg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;productsign&lt;/code&gt; is the utility in charge of the signing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--sign&lt;/code&gt; is the argument that defines the Identity associated to the Apple issued certificated, which follows as a string.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;./installer.pkg&lt;/code&gt; is the relative path (can be absolute as well) that points to the file you want to be signed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;./installer_signed.pkg&lt;/code&gt; is the path of the new, signed file that is going to be created by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;productsign&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course you should substitute the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;Developer ID Installer:&quot;&lt;/code&gt; string with the one you’ve noted in the previous section, as well as the files paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can verify that the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;installer_signed.pkg&lt;/code&gt; has been really signed with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pkgutil --check-signature ./installer_signed.pkg

   Status: signed by a certificate trusted by Mac OS X
   Certificate Chain:
    1. Developer ID Installer: Davide Barranca (Y4PA7PZLM9)
       SHA1 fingerprint: 3A 7C 3D 1E 28 AA 54 83 E5 E8 11 7F 2A 12 ED C7 17
       --------------------------------------------------------------------    2. Developer ID Certification Authority
       SHA1 fingerprint: 3B 16 6C 3B CC C4 B7 11 C9 FE 22 FA B9 13 56 41 E3       --------------------------------------------------------------------    3. Apple Root CA
       SHA1 fingerprint: 61 1E 5B A2 2C 59 3A 08 FF 58 D1 61 E2 24 52 D1 98       
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-sending-the-notarization-request&quot;&gt;3. Sending the notarization request&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep handy the app-specific password you’ve requested from your AppleID account (if you’ve not done it yet, follow the instruction &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT204397&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Let’s say that it is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cvbs-epfg-sizx-olwd&lt;/code&gt;. The command I’ve used to request the notarization is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xcrun altool --notarize-app --primary-bundle-id &quot;com.ccextensions.alce3&quot; --username &quot;YourAppleID@mail.com&quot; --password &quot;cvbs-epfg-sizx-olwd&quot; --file &quot;/full/path/to/the/installer_signed.pkg&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xcrun&lt;/code&gt; is used to find and execute XCode commands.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;altool&lt;/code&gt; is the executable that performs the notarization request.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--notarize-app&lt;/code&gt; is the flag that tells &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;altool&lt;/code&gt; to request notarization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--primary-bundle-id&lt;/code&gt; links to the installer I’m submitting its unique &lt;em&gt;bundle id&lt;/em&gt; (in my case &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;com.ccextensions.alce3&quot;&lt;/code&gt;, substitute it with yours)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--username&lt;/code&gt; wants your AppleID.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--password&lt;/code&gt; wants the app-specific password you’ve requested (here, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;cvbs-epfg-sizx-olwd&quot;&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--file&lt;/code&gt; is the flag that tells &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;altool&lt;/code&gt; which file to upload. Please note that I had to specify the absolute full path (not the relative that starts with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;./&lt;/code&gt;) between quotes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command takes a while to upload the file, and gives you zero feedback; after a while, if the process has been successful, you get back something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;2019-09-18 16:30:35.659 altool[8788:92462] No errors uploading '/full/path/to/the/installer_signed.pkg'.
RequestUUID = 181638fb-a618-2298-bff0-47fa79f01326
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep note of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RequestUUID&lt;/code&gt; string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point your request for notarizationhas been sent to Apple, and you have to wait for them to process the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind you: if you get &lt;strong&gt;“Error: You must first sign the relevant contracts online. (1048)”&lt;/strong&gt; (as it has happened to me several times) don’t panic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can launch XCode to check whether it asks you to accept its Terms and Conditions, or run the following command to agree from the Terminal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo xcodebuild -license
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then try checking at &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunesconnect.apple.com/&quot;&gt;iTunesConnect&lt;/a&gt;, in the section “Agreements, Tax and Banking”. The “Paid Apps” list item may have a Status of “Pending User Information”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:itc&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:itc&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but there shouldn’t be any Agreement pending (usually their warnings are listed separately).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, still, nothing works it may be a glitch on Apple’s side, so wait a couple of hours and try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-checking-the-notarization-status&quot;&gt;4. Checking the notarization status&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Terminal, enter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xcrun altool --notarization-info 181638fb-a618-2298-bff0-47fa79f01326 --username &quot;YourAppleID@mail.com&quot; --password &quot;cvbs-epfg-sizx-olwd&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command uses now &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--notarization-info&lt;/code&gt; to ping the current status, and expects the same &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RequestUUID&lt;/code&gt; string that has been sent you in response of the original request. The result is something like that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;2019-09-18 16:31:48.449 altool[9133:95654] No errors getting notarization info.

   RequestUUID: 181638fb-a618-2298-bff0-47fa79f01326
          Date: 2019-09-18 14:30:36 +0000
        Status: in progress
    LogFileURL: (null)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note the &lt;em&gt;in progress&lt;/em&gt; status. At some point the result will be different, and hopefully similar to this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;   RequestUUID: 287628eb-e628-4998-b4b0-47fa79f07386
          Date: 2019-09-18 14:30:36 +0000
        Status: success
    LogFileURL: https://osxapps-ssl.itunes.apple.com/awfully/long/URL
    Status Code: 0
Status Message: Package Approved
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The installer has been successfully notarized!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, for some reason, you have to perform several requests and want to check the notarization requests history, run the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xcrun altool --notarization-history 0 --username &quot;YourAppleID@mail.com&quot; --password &quot;cvbs-epfg-sizx-olwd&quot;

Notarization History - page 0

Date                      RequestUUID                          Status  Status Code Status Message   
------------------------- ------------------------------------ ------- ----------- ----------------
2019-09-18 14:30:36 +0000 181638fb-a618-2298-bff0-47fa79f01326 success 0           Package Approved

Next page value: 1768817026000

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-stapling-the-ticket-to-the-file&quot;&gt;5. Stapling the ticket to the file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote, this step is optional but highly recommended: Gatekeeper will be able to find the whitelist info in the file itself, without the need to perform an online check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xcrun stapler staple &quot;/full/path/to/the/installer_signed.pkg&quot;

Processing: /full/path/to/the/installer_signed.pkg
The staple and validate action worked!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command here is much simpler: you don’t need to pass any &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RequestUUID&lt;/code&gt; string yourself, for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;stapler&lt;/code&gt; will do the call home at Apple’s on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check stapling details with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stapler validate --verbose &quot;/full/path/to/the/installer_signed.pkg&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is too long to paste here, and frankly I’ve no idea what it means: as long as it ends with &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;The validate action worked!&quot;&lt;/code&gt; you should be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And… &lt;strong&gt;you’re done&lt;/strong&gt; 🍾&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience the Notarization can take from 60 seconds up to many hours (one time I’ve had the Terminal waiting and checking the status from 3PM to midnight). In theory it should be fast, in practice you can occasionally run into long delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caveats-for-different-scenarios&quot;&gt;Caveats for different scenarios&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example I’ve shown is for one &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;installer.pkg&lt;/code&gt; file. Let’s say that you (as I do) deliver to your customers a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;product.dmg&lt;/code&gt; file, that wraps the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;installer.pkg&lt;/code&gt;, an additional &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;uninstaller.app&lt;/code&gt; (say, an &lt;em&gt;app-ified&lt;/em&gt; AppleScript) and some documentation as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, you need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Notarize only the outmost container (here the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.dmg&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign all the executable children elements (here the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.app&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pkg&lt;/code&gt;) &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.dmg&lt;/code&gt; as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that in order to sign a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.dmg&lt;/code&gt; you need a “Developer ID Application” certificate, instead of the “Developer ID Installer” I’ve used for the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.pkg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, things may get a bit convoluted when it comes to extra libraries/bundles that may be called by your panel – if you feel like it’s your case, please read &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.developer.apple.com/message/383180&quot;&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-dmg-canvas&quot;&gt;UPDATE: DMG Canvas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The software that I use, and recommend, to build &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.dmg&lt;/code&gt; files is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.araelium.com/dmgcanvas&quot;&gt;Araelium DMG Canvas&lt;/a&gt;, which has recently bumped to version 3.x (a paid upgrade, around $10). One of the new features is the possibility to automate the notarization process while building the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.dmg&lt;/code&gt; itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/DMGCanvas.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/DMGCanvas.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/05/DMGCanvas@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;DMG Canvas&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tell you the truth, the first product I’ve used that for went flawlessly, and in a snap; the second product failed due to a timeout, which sounds very much an Apple issue rather than Araelium’s. Please note that DMG Canvas does the stapling too, which is quite handy, and can be automatized to fit your build system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-uninstaller-app&quot;&gt;UPDATE: Uninstaller app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve finally upgraded my machine to Catalina, I’m able to experience the entire, happy spectrum of Catalina-related issues. I’ve discovered that with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Uninstall.app&lt;/code&gt; the signature I’ve been doing is not enough: the notarization of the outer &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.dmg&lt;/code&gt; fails with the error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;The executable does not have the hardened runtime enabled.&quot;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the case, be aware that you should &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; export the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Uninstall.scpt&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Uninstall.app&lt;/code&gt; while signing it with the Script Editor (it’s an option in the File &amp;gt; Export dialog). Instead, export it without signature and then use the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;codesign&lt;/code&gt; utility with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-o runtime&lt;/code&gt; flag:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;codesign -s &quot;Developer ID Application: Davide Barranca&quot; -o runtime /path/to/Uninstall.app
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it might happen that the signing process of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.app&lt;/code&gt; fails because of the error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;resource fork, Finder information, or similar detritus not allowed&quot;&lt;/code&gt;. You can spot such digital &lt;em&gt;detritus&lt;/em&gt; running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xattr -lr /path/to/Uninstall.app

/path/to/Uninstall.app: com.apple.FinderInfo:
00000000  50 4C 41 50 6C 74 61 70 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00  |PLAPltap........|
00000010  00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00  |................|
00000020
/path/to/Uninstall.app: com.apple.metadata:_kMDItemUserTags:
00000000  62 70 6C 69 73 74 30 30 A0 08 00 00 00 00 00 00  |bplist00........|
00000010  01 01 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 01 00 00 00 00 00 00  |................|
00000020  00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00 09                    |..........|
0000002a
/path/to/Uninstall.app: com.apple.metadata:kMDLabel_vtos3pl2xookcnywmtbwlcbnry:
00000000  F2 20 2F 2C 8B D7 B3 8E B9 A9 39 DD 12 79 01 05  |. /,......9..y..|
00000010  BB 76 D8 72 90 73 F2 E9 B2 A3 2A 79 4F 5C 76 F0  |.v.r.s....*yO.v.|
00000020  5B 09 C3 8C 53 5D 90 FA 6D 27 2C 00 86 5E 57 7C  |[...S]..m',..^W||
00000030  DF F9 0B 78 83 19 F9 CA 48 6D 66 21 E9 D9 A8 D4  |...x....Hmf!....|
00000040  5E D2 52 53 A1 94 97 94 C4 3C ED A1 89 FF D4 5B  |^.RS.....&amp;lt;.....[|
00000050  AB 17 0F 53 4F 8A 75 85 FD                       |...SO.u..|
00000059
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clean that mess (whatever it is), run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xattr -cr /path/to/Uninstall.app
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and the subsequent &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;codesign&lt;/code&gt; should complete with no problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;support-this-site&quot;&gt;Support this site!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please consider supporting my work with the purchase of these books and courses. You can find them all &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidebarranca.com/courses/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, bundles available. Thanks! 🙏🏻&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidebarranca.com/courses/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/courses.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/courses.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/05/courses@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Courses&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. I will update the Ultimate Guide to Native Installers and Automated Build Systems as well, I just wanted you to get informed asap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:itc&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you don’t plan to sell through Apple, there’s no point in filling the uber-annoying Tax forms, etc. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:itc&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/notarizing-installers-for-macos-catalina/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/notarizing-installers-for-macos-catalina/</guid>
        
        <category>Notarizing</category>
        
        <category>Apple</category>
        
        <category>macOS Catalina</category>
        
        
        <category>HTML Panels tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Printing on demand a Leanpub book with Lulu.com</title>
        <description>&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;
table { padding: 0; border-collapse: collapse; margin: auto auto }
table tr {
  border-top: 1px solid #cccccc;
  background-color: white;
  margin: 0;
  padding: 0;
}
table tr:nth-child(2n) {
  background-color: #f8f8f8;
}
table tr th {
  font-weight: bold;
  border: 1px solid #cccccc;
  margin: 0;
  padding: 6px 13px;
}
table tr td {
  border: 1px solid #cccccc;
  margin: 0;
  padding: 6px 13px;
}
table tr th :first-child, table tr td :first-child {
  margin-top: 0;
}
table tr th :last-child, table tr td :last-child {
  margin-bottom: 0;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/ProPSScriptingWithBloom.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/ProPSScriptingWithBloom.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/ProPSScriptingWithBloom@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Leanpub&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;And this shall be mine, human...&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authoring a book is awesome – especially when you’re done with it – but holding an actual object in your hands still gives a special kind of thrill. I’ve just run an ultra-small print batch of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ps-scripting.com/&quot;&gt;Professional Photoshop Scripting&lt;/a&gt; book, that I have self-published with Leanpub and printed-on-demand with Lulu: in this post I’m going to describe the whole process, what I’ve learned from it, and what I’d do differently to make the result even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There is some room for improvement but all considered I am pleased!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In my daytime job I also do some books designing for my client, when asked; I have a decent understanding of printing process’ technical aspects in general, and I am familiar with the related software. In a previous life of mine I’ve been a color-management consultant for press/pre-press too. Nonetheless, this whole “get the book printed!” business took me by surprise, and I wanted to go through it as swiftly as possible; as a consequence, I admit to have taken, sometimes, the quickest path (i.e., not the best one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-have-i-got-a-printed-version-of-my-book-in-the-first-place&quot;&gt;Why have I got a printed version of my book in the first place?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to; I mean, it wasn’t planned when I was writing it. Jeffrey Tranberry (&lt;em&gt;Sr. Product Manager, Digital Imaging at Adobe Systems&lt;/em&gt;, and long time Scripting advocate) has very kindly accepted to write the book’s foreword: he’s gotten in touch with me a few weeks later asking if it was possible for him to receive a signed copy. Sure, I’d be glad to! Although it took me a moment to get accustomed to the idea that I, Davide, was the one supposed to sign a book for Jeff and not the other way around – in 2012 he wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Power-Speed-Automation-Adobe-Photoshop-ebook/dp/B0083JCBZ2/&quot;&gt;Power, Speed &amp;amp; Automation with Adobe Photoshop&lt;/a&gt; with Geoff Scott, the only other book on earth that touches PS Scripting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem was that I had no actual printed book to send, just a PDF. I felt morally obliged to fulfill Jeff’s fair request as soon as possible, so I started my research for an online, print-on-demand service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-an-ebook-with-leanpub&quot;&gt;Creating an ebook with Leanpub&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point was an ebook that I self published with &lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com/&quot;&gt;Leanpub&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re not familiar with them, you are allowed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] write books in Markdown (our dialect is called Markua), Google Docs or our visual editor, and publish an ebook (in PDF, EPUB and MOBI) with one click. The Leanpub store helps you sell your book while it’s in-progress, getting reader feedback and earning 80% royalties. Or, upload a completed ebook to sell in our store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Leanpub.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Leanpub.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Leanpub@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Leanpub&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Leanpub book's author backend page&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I couldn’t recommend Leanpub more&lt;/strong&gt;, seriously: as a company, they offer extra services that I don’t really need (book landing page, e-commerce, in-progress publishing, etc), but their writing platform alone is superb. I’ve already used Leanpub for my previous book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.htmlpanelsbook.com/&quot;&gt;Adobe Photoshop HTML Panels Development&lt;/a&gt;, hence I was no stranger to the whole process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took some R&amp;amp;D time to evaluate alternative options within my reach: I could use InDesign, iBooks Author, write in MarkDown and convert to PDF with Softcover or Pandoc&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Pandoc&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Pandoc&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After some pondering, I decided that they all required too much efforts on my side to customize the result compared to Leanpub design, which was excellent out-of-the-box; and so I went with it. The book in itself was already a tough enterprise to undertake, I’d be better off spending my time on content creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;writing-in-markdown&quot;&gt;Writing in MarkDown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To briefly describe the process, &lt;strong&gt;I’ve written the entire book in MarkDown&lt;/strong&gt; – a textual format with handy shortcuts, e.g., &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_italic_&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;**bold**&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;[^footnotes]&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;![Images](graphic.png)&lt;/code&gt; and everything else a writer may need –, keeping the files in synch with Leanpub via Dropbox&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hook&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hook&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Markdown.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Markdown.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Markdown@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Markdown&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Using the MWeb app to write and preview MarkDown.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve used &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://macdown.uranusjr.com/&quot;&gt;MacDown&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mweb.im/&quot;&gt;MWeb&lt;/a&gt; to write MarkDown, yet there’s plenty of apps (free or paid) available, even if to the best of my knowledge none of them supports the Leanpub’s &lt;em&gt;flavour&lt;/em&gt;.  In the last years they have been working on the specs of &lt;a href=&quot;http://markua.com/&quot;&gt;Markua&lt;/a&gt;, a MarkDown superset that specifically targets eBooks creation; it is already available as an option to authors, but besides Leanpub’s Markua online editor I don’t think there are apps for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can trigger the book compilation on-demand, either the entire content or just an excerpt to make the task quicker; the compilation itself is performed &lt;em&gt;on their servers&lt;/em&gt; and the results (PDF, ePub and MOBI files) uploaded to a shared Dropbox folder automatically. This is the main Leanpub’s downside, in my opinion: depending on the amount of content you’ve written, &lt;strong&gt;the PDF generation process can take few minutes&lt;/strong&gt; to complete: besides the transformation from MarkDown to PDF&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:md2pdf&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:md2pdf&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, you have to wait for the files to get uploaded to Dropbox, and downloaded locally. Alas, we’re not used to waiting anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the PDF, which is what you’d use for printing purposes, their book design has a &lt;strong&gt;classic and professional look&lt;/strong&gt;, very well suited to technical publishing like my project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/BookDesign.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/BookDesign.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/BookDesign@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Book Design&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Leanpub book's design is professional and well balanced&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that using a markup language also means that your content follows well defined formatting rules; while you focus on the writing, the book “composes itself”, so to speak. On the other side you don’t have pixel-perfect elements positioning as with, say,  InDesign. Some trial and error is intrinsic to the process, but it inevitably extends the waiting time in-between PDF generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exporting-for-print&quot;&gt;Exporting for print&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leanpub has a specific Export option called &lt;strong&gt;Print-Ready PDF&lt;/strong&gt;, that is the one you should pick when your goal is ink on paper. It slightly differs from the traditional screen output, quoting from their website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has no cover image. Services like KDP and Lulu want you to upload a wraparound cover, so our ebook cover image would be redundant. Instead, it starts with the inside cover.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has alternating page numbers, so that they end up on the outside corners. (The outside corners are the ones which are away from the book spine.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has alternating margins: the inside margins are often wider than the outside margins, so that you can actually see the text on the inside margins. (The inside margins are the ones which are next to the book spine.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has occasional blank pages to ensure that chapters start on the right side.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an alternative &lt;strong&gt;Export InDesign Files&lt;/strong&gt; option that outputs InCopy &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.icml&lt;/code&gt; files, one per chapter: your job is to manually insert each chapter in a provided, dummy InDesign &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.indd&lt;/code&gt; file, which you can then customize to your book designer taste. Since I was in hurry, and Leanpub had a (now fixed) bug in the InDesign Export, I postulated that the Print-Ready PDF was a good enough starting point for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;choosing-a-print-on-demand-service&quot;&gt;Choosing a print-on-demand service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dear friend and Photoshop retoucher &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorduels.com/&quot;&gt;Daniele Di Stanio&lt;/a&gt; promptly pointed me to an article titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@mwichary/my-experiences-printing-a-small-batch-of-books-c04141b63dfe&quot;&gt;My experiences printing a small batch of books&lt;/a&gt;”. The goal of the post’s author was to publish&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“a simple, old-school book with… letters in it”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I.e., a novel. My book, instead, is in the &lt;strong&gt;technical publishing&lt;/strong&gt; category (software development), with illustrations, screenshots, few photographs and a lot of syntax highlighted code. Our needs didn’t really match, but it was a well-thought comparison of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blurb.com/getting-started#&quot;&gt;Blurb&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bookbaby.com/print-on-demand&quot;&gt;BookBaby&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://xpress.lulu.com/our-products&quot;&gt;Lulu&lt;/a&gt; and Nook Press (now &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.barnesandnoble.com/print-on-demand/&quot;&gt;Barnes and Noble Press&lt;/a&gt;) anyway. For a while, I’ve evaluated local, Italy-based services as well, yet the price-tag was way too high; I also tried to understand how &lt;a href=&quot;https://kdp.amazon.com/en_US/&quot;&gt;Kindle Direct Publishing&lt;/a&gt; works, but I couldn’t get whether the printed books must be sold via Amazon or could be directly shipped to the author, so I gave it up&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:time&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:time&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. If you have experience of KDP, please let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every print-on-demand (POD) service provider offers some sort of “Make your book” page where you choose the book’s options, such as Size, Binding, Paper and Inks, etc. and gives you an estimate of the cost per copy. Depending on the print batch size, small discounts may apply as well. I suggest you to go through that process for all the PODs that you want to test, to understand which one better suits your needs and budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;printing-with-lulu&quot;&gt;Printing with Lulu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, I decided to go with &lt;a href=&quot;https://xpress.lulu.com/our-products&quot;&gt;Lulu&lt;/a&gt;; probably other PODs could have worked fine too – after all I don’t have ultra-specific needs –, but one can’t keep splitting hairs in two for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;books-options&quot;&gt;Book’s options&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Lulu’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://xpress.lulu.com/pricing&quot;&gt;Book Pricing Calculator page&lt;/a&gt; I could test how the various options affected the price per copy; besides a large variety of book sizes, the main choices were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Binding&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hardcover Casewrap (traditional hardcover, stitched)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Perfect Bound” (milled/glued)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Coil bound (with plastic coil)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inks&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Standard B/W&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Standard Color&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Premium B/W&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Premium Color&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;60# Cream Uncoated&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;60# White Uncoated&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;80# White Coated&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few remarks.&lt;br /&gt;
Lulu’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://xpress.lulu.com/our-products&quot;&gt;Producs descriptions&lt;/a&gt; fall a bit short of tech specs: each option is related to the final result instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PrintOptions.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PrintOptions.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PrintOptions@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Print Options&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Standard Color is &lt;em&gt;“Ideal for text-heavy content with a few color images, graphs, or illustrations that have low to moderate ink coverage”&lt;/em&gt; whereas Premium Color’s &lt;em&gt;“Ideal for image-heavy content with heavy ink coverage on the pages”&lt;/em&gt;. I can understand this, but it tells nothing about the kind of inks used, print resolution, the Total Ink Coverage allowed, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PerfectBound.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PerfectBound.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PerfectBound@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;PerfectBound&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Binding options are illustrated with photographs of the final object, no such close-up pictures are given for Paper types or Inks. I suppose 60# and 80# refers to the paper weight, in grams per square meter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PaperTypes.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PaperTypes.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/PaperTypes@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Paper types&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that my original PDF was US Letter (8.5x11 inches) sized, 400-ish pages long, this is the cost per copy for a variety of different Ink, Paper, Binding combinations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Ink&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Paper&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Binding&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;Price&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Color Standard&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;60# Uncoated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Perfect Bound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$17.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Color Standard&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Perfect Bound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$19.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;B/W Standard&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Perfect Bound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$9.80&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;B/W Premium&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Perfect Bound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$15.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;B/W Premium&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Casewrap&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$22.75&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Color Premium&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Perfect Bound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$65.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Color Premium&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Perfect Bound&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$65.40&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Color Premium&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Casewrap&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;$72.50&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My book is quite long, so keep that in mind when evaluating prices. Printing with Lulu goes from a nice $9.80 for a Black &amp;amp; White Standard Inks on the best paper with glued/milled binding, to a surprising $72.50 for the top quality options in all departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that the paper choice doesn’t really influence the price that much, $2.00 spread over four hundred pages is half of a Cent difference per page, so &lt;strong&gt;80# Coated White&lt;/strong&gt; was a no brainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inks make the greatest difference of all: +$5.60 to upgrade from B/W Standard to B/W Premium; +$4.00 from B/W Premium to Color Standard, and a whopping +$46 to get from Color Standard to Color Premium! I understand that the more expensive option is for Photo Books, which mine is not, out of question/budget. I was left deciding between B/W Premium and Color Standard: since I have several graphics in color, pictures and syntax highlighted code, I thought that it’d be cheap to print grayscale so I went with &lt;strong&gt;Color Standard Inks&lt;/strong&gt;. Finger crossed for the &lt;em&gt;“few color images, graphs, or illustrations that have low to moderate ink coverage”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should have picked Casewrap (the hardcover, stitched binding option), but +$7.10 looked too much for the cheapskate I’ve become in my forties, so I got &lt;strong&gt;Perfect Bound&lt;/strong&gt; with a glossy finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final price was around $20 per copy; I ordered the titanic amount of 3 copies, which added $23 in Ground Courier Shipment, 4/5 days to wait. With my country’s VAT, all this print-on-demand test of mine was worth something more than $90, or about $30 per copy in total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-the-pdf&quot;&gt;Preparing the PDF&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section is going to be a bit technical: if you happen to read this post because you want to Lulu-print your own book and it’s not text only (e.g., a novel or poetry), try asking a graphic designer for help. Being subscribed to the Adobe Creative Cloud, I have access to software such as Acrobat DC, InDesign and Photoshop, that I’ve used extensively here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grab all Lulu’s relevant &lt;strong&gt;documentation PDFs&lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://toolkit.lulu.com/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;, and give it a read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, duplicate your Leanpub Print-Ready PDF. Open it in Acrobat and add the recommended &lt;strong&gt;bleed&lt;/strong&gt; – in my case 0.125”; make sure you have a single page (not spreads) PDF with an even number of pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Bleed.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Bleed.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Bleed@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Bleed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;strong&gt;Transparency Flattener&lt;/strong&gt;, Lulu provides a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lulu-High-Res-Outlines.flst&lt;/code&gt; preset file: you can’t use it in Acrobat, only when exporting to PDF from InDesign. But from InDesign you can edit it to find out what the settings are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Transparency.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Transparency.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Transparency@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Transparency&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fine with everything but converting the text to outline, so I run the built-in Acrobat Transparency Flattener at high resolution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Flattener.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Flattener.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Flattener@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Flattener&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve then run a &lt;strong&gt;preflight&lt;/strong&gt; against PDF/X-1a, fixing the errors when possible. I’ve manually substituted images which were too low-res for the print version (but OK for screen/display visualization).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to &lt;strong&gt;Color Management&lt;/strong&gt;, things are a bit fuzzy: Lulu provides two sets of JobOptions, &lt;a href=&quot;http://connect.lulu.com/en/discussion/32882/how-to-make-a-pdf-using-adobe-indesign&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://connect.lulu.com/en/discussion/33681/pdf-creation-settings-how-can-i-be-sure-my-pdf-will-print-correctly&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, with of instruction contrasting with each other, or with information that Lulu provides in the Guides. For instance, I’ve read to convert everything to sRGB, and Leave Color Unchanged at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;http://connect.lulu.com/en/discussion/353421/joboptions-and-colormanagement/&quot;&gt;asked in their forums&lt;/a&gt;, and they opened a support ticket for me. After a couple of very kind emails, I got this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They have ongoing partnerships with several print facilities in different places in the world (US, Canada, Europe, and Australia).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They have agreed with each contractor on a set of quality standards (based on ink/paper), although their print partners are largely autonomous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They tend to suggest sRGB to standardize the color input (and avoid problems).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is not possible to micro-manage (prepress-style) graphic elements in the PDF (custom CMYK separations, GCR, etc) for each print shop may do &lt;em&gt;CMYK repurposing&lt;/em&gt; on their own e.g., for color management or ink saving purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also explains why the product description is not very much detailed, but based on broad quality definitions. Reluctantly, I made sure that everything was &lt;strong&gt;converted to sRGB&lt;/strong&gt; and did upload the PDF to Lulu’s servers – hoping that the pre-press gods wouldn’t notice my sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/sRGB.png&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/sRGB.png 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/sRGB@2x.png 2x&quot; alt=&quot;sRGB&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you’re wondering, I didn’t go on asking which print facility my order would have been sent to (somewhere in south UK, it turned out), with the idea of getting in touch with their prepress department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;strong&gt;cover&lt;/strong&gt;, Lulu provides an InDesign template and a Spine width calculator (based on the binding type and pages number) – creating the design from scratch wasn’t difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Cover.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Cover.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Cover@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Cover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole online order creation process is guided, and almost impossible to mess up when you have all the assets ready. I paid with PayPal, and the book got printed I think the next day, and arrived in my hands in a few days later as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-printed-result&quot;&gt;The printed result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to be judgmental the very moment you hold for the first time a printed copy of the work that took 1.5 years of your life to complete: it looked awesome, and at the same time I was so fed up with the entire project that I gave it a quick review, wrote an affectionate dedication to Jeffrey, prepared the package and sent it to Adobe’s offices in Minnesota, US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Spread.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Spread.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Spread@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Spread&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, you can read below a frank bullet-points list of what I liked, what I didn’t really like, what was my fault and what I’d do differently next time to get a better result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video width=&quot;680&quot; height=&quot;382&quot; controls=&quot;controls&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; margin: 0 auto; height: auto; display: block; border: 0;&quot;&gt;
&lt;source src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/FlippingPages.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-good-parts&quot;&gt;The good parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;paper&lt;/strong&gt; is nice: it looks very much like an 80g/mq, the coating is OK, it surely has some optical brighteners but it’s not obviously bluish/greenish.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;print quality&lt;/strong&gt; is OK too. I was a bit worried about some pages with higher ink coverage, but in general there are no ghosting problems, stains and such. The color rendition and gray balance are fine too. Usually, software development books are printed in B/W, but given the limited batch I’ve ordered, it made little sense to save few bucks on B/W inks. Would I need a larger number of copies, I’d surely go for it. In case, it would be nice to have an 80 grams uncoated paper, but Lulu offers 60 only without coating.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;binding&lt;/strong&gt; is robust, not the kind of book that looks like it will shred pages around the fifth time you open it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;  
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Binding.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Binding.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Binding@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Binding&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;PerfectBound looks sturdy indeed&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bad-parts&quot;&gt;The bad parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or at least the ones I personally find not up my expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;package&lt;/strong&gt; wasn’t particularly good: the usual cardboard box with little protection against corners damage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The soft &lt;strong&gt;cover&lt;/strong&gt; is rather fragile, especially along edges, where the glossy coat may get slightly peeled off. I’d be curious to see whether a matte finish is less delicate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;  
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Peeled.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Peeled.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Peeled@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Peeled glossy finish&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Glossy finish peeling off&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not being able to micro-manage the &lt;strong&gt;color separations&lt;/strong&gt; still bugs me a bit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is some &lt;strong&gt;banding&lt;/strong&gt; here and there, that somehow I expected on a digital printed book. Probably the pricey “Color Premium inks” option deals with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;  
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Banding.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Banding.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Banding@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Banding&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Dark and light Banding on the sky&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-mistakes&quot;&gt;My mistakes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;book size&lt;/strong&gt; I chose is too big to my taste. This is something I couldn’t change&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:change&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:change&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;: it would have meant re-checking all the elements flow, and I had no time for that. When you start writing your eBook, even if you don’t plan to print it, think about the physical size of the page: PDF area is one thing, paper surface is another. I went with US Letter (8.5x11 inches, 21.6x27.9cm): other books in the software development category are smaller, like 18x23.5cm (O’Reilly) or 1cm wider (Packt), so around 7-7.5x9.2 inches. Mine looks unnecessarily large.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I didn’t check all the &lt;strong&gt;images resolution&lt;/strong&gt; properly, so you can spot some pixelation here and there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never, ever take &lt;strong&gt;dark interface programs’ screenshots&lt;/strong&gt;. Dark interfaces are cool to use, eye-relaxing to look at, moderately nice in PDFs, dreadful in print, for legibility is compromised. My code’s syntax highlighting was great on the printed page, for it uses a light theme: don’t even think about using a dark theme for it. Also, I’m not 100% sure to have converted to sRGB all the screenshots when taking them&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:ICC&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:ICC&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not my mistake but it’s not clear either (I’ve to check with Leanpub on that) whether or not the Print-Ready PDF export option downsamples images. It may make sense for display PDFs, not so for Print where it is desirable to keep the max resolution available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I am really pleased with the result. It took me some time to figure out the workflow for I was a first timer and I got some things wrong, but I can do better next time (even if I do not plan to offer my book in a printed version anytime soon). The materials are OK, the price is fair for a micro print batch such as mine. I’m curious to hear your experiences with print-on-demand services, so please share it in the comments section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I didn’t tell you the entire story…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff offered me the possibility to send him two copies of my book: one as a well deserved gift to him, the other… would be sent me back with signatures by the Photoshop teams from both the Minnesota and California offices! Accidentally, &lt;em&gt;“somebody”&lt;/em&gt; 🙏🏻 let also some tattoos, stickers, a pin and a shirt slip into the package, so I’ve now some Photoshop branded swag in the house, for my daughter to steal me&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:wand&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:wand&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Signatures.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Signatures.jpg 1x, /wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Signatures@2x.jpg 2x&quot; alt=&quot;Signatures&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Adobe Photoshop team signatures from Minnesota and California offices&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t that &lt;strong&gt;awesome&lt;/strong&gt;?! ❤️&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Pandoc&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandoc.org/&quot;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source conversion tool that is also able to export to PDF from MarkDown, but the styling part is time consuming and you got to have quite some LaTeX knowledge. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.softcover.io/&quot;&gt;Softcover&lt;/a&gt; is a free alternative to Leanpub for the MarkDown to PDF part, but it requires more customization efforts, a bit of LaTeX skills and the resulting book style isn’t as good as Leanpub’s. Both have the notable upside that the entire process is local, whereas Leanpub creates the PDF server-side. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Pandoc&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hook&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The whole book was within a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; repository, with an optional hook so that each push triggered the book compilation. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hook&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:md2pdf&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Leanpub conversion uses an intermediate LaTeX step, so it’s actually MarkDown to LaTeX to PDF. It is very likely that, internally, thay make use of Pandoc heavily tweaked with custom LaTeX styling. Which is what allows Text Blocks with Icons, Syntax Highlighting and all the features that make Leanpub ebooks so nice. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:md2pdf&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:time&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It all may sound a bit sloppy now, but back then I really felt like I was in hurry: with more time, I could have evaluated options more carefully. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:time&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:change&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Leanpub lets you pick a different page size when you export the Print-Ready PDF, but as I’ve written I had no time to check +400 pages again to look for, and fix, misplaced elements. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:change&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:ICC&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On Mac, when you take a screenshot it is assigned the Display’s ICC profile. If you save the PNG/JPG with the embedded ICC, it gets properly converted to sRGB in the PDF post-production stage; if, by mistake, you discard the ICC profile while saving, sRGB is assigned (and therefore not converted) in the PDF, and colors will shift. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:ICC&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:wand&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;She’s got a Magic Wand tattoo on her forearm that she wiggles around the house like Hermione Granger. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:wand&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/printing-leanpub-books-on-lulu/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/printing-leanpub-books-on-lulu/</guid>
        
        <category>Leanpub</category>
        
        <category>Lulu</category>
        
        <category>Print-on-demand</category>
        
        
        <category>Personal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Migrating from WordPress to Jekyll on Netlify</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After years, I’ve been able to kiss WordPress bye-bye and migrate to a fully static site build with Jekyll and deployed to Netlify. In this post I’ll tell you why, and show you how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-not-wordpress&quot;&gt;Why not WordPress?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve nothing against WP in principle, it’s not the right tool for me. I blogpost on average once a month, it makes no sense for me to be bound to a Linux hosting with mySQL access, a BackupBuddy subscription plan and a dozen of other WP plugins to run this site. Have you seen my posts? A couple of images, few snippets of code, some text. Really, WP is plain overkill; plus, I don’t want to worry about WP updates, PhpMyAdmin, DB access errors, log-ins, plugin incompatibility and fancy dashboards anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have a simpler, static site which I update writing text files on my disk, committing to a free git repository, which Jekyll files are automatically built, hosted and served over https for free by Netlify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;static-vs-dynamic&quot;&gt;Static vs. Dynamic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As opposed to WP, where each PHP &lt;em&gt;template&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:template&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:template&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is filled on-demand – i.e. when a user requests a page, fetching the content from a database and returning the processed data as html – a Static site is &lt;em&gt;pre-compiled&lt;/em&gt; so to speak, and simply made available online all at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence, a WP site needs a machine running some server-side scripting language such as PHP, a database like mySQL, and some processing resources; a static site is happy when it is hosted on a server that is (a) turned on, and (b) connected to the net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ssgs&quot;&gt;SSGs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with the concept of Static Site Generators, they’re command-line tools that get a bunch of HTML/JS/CSS with template code and markdown files as input, and output a full static website. Your job is then to move the files on the server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several SSGs available: to the best of my knowledge, the most popular ones are &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; (written in Ruby), &lt;a href=&quot;https://gohugo.io&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; (written in Go) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hexo.io/&quot;&gt;Hexo&lt;/a&gt; (Javascript). Each one of them has its peculiar templating system and folders structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.staticgen.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/staticGen.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;If you feel inclined, a way too big list of SSGs is found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.staticgen.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of them share the sublime idea that you compose your writing (both pages and blog-posts) in MarkDown: a text file with a basic set of formatting rules, such as **&lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;**, _&lt;em&gt;italic&lt;/em&gt;_ etc. Hence, all your website content is not hidden into some resources-hungry DataBase, but exposed to you as plain text files with a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;which-ssg-to-pick&quot;&gt;Which SSG to pick&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you start fresh (i.e., you don’t run a SSG already) or you don’t have plenty of time on your hands, I suggest you to look at the available templates for Jekyll (&lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllthemes.io&quot;&gt;free&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllthemes.io/premium&quot;&gt;paid&lt;/a&gt;), for &lt;a href=&quot;https://themes.gohugo.io/&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; and for &lt;a href=&quot;https://hexo.io/themes/&quot;&gt;Hexo&lt;/a&gt;. Beware high expectations: they’re all quite &lt;em&gt;bare&lt;/em&gt;. Pick the one you like the most, and then learn that templating language to customize it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a superficial level, that’s all you need. To me – and I’m not really into SSGs enough to get all the nuances – besides the templating language, the only other difference is compilation speed. Being written in Go, &lt;strong&gt;Hugo goes like a rocket&lt;/strong&gt;. My website is compiled by Hugo in 1.5 seconds, whereas Jekyll takes ~14 seconds, and Hexo is not that much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/hugo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hugo vs. Jekyll&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that each time you modify a thing and save, the process re-generates (if you want, incrementally) the whole website, so 14 seconds to see whether a CSS rule or a template tweak really do what you originally meant them to do, may be a long time to wait – the fifth time in a row that you hit save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am on Jekyll, using a mildly customized version of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://themeforest.net/item/steve-a-minimal-blog-theme-for-jekyll/15601096&quot;&gt;Steve theme&lt;/a&gt;, which costed me like $15. I already run &lt;a href=&quot;https://cc-extensions.com/&quot;&gt;CC-Extensions&lt;/a&gt; on Jekyll, I’m mildly familiar with it, so I’ll keep being patient if it takes seconds to compile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wordpress-migration&quot;&gt;WordPress migration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve followed this very checklist myself. Perhaps things can be made simpler, but this has worked fine for me – feel free to google stuff if you need more detailed information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Migrate all your comments to &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;: sign up and follow the instruction to install Disqus on WordPress (you’ll need to get &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/plugins/disqus-comment-system/&quot;&gt;this WP Plugin&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do a full backup: I’ve always used &lt;a href=&quot;https://ithemes.com/purchase/backupbuddy/&quot;&gt;BackupBuddy&lt;/a&gt;, which isn’t cheap but works like a charm – perhaps also the built-in WP Export is OK. You need to backup both the WP assets and the DB.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mamp.info/&quot;&gt;MAMP&lt;/a&gt; or a similar software and restore your WordPress installation on a local server (e.g. on your laptop). This will make the following step faster.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On your local WP, install both &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SchumacherFM/wordpress-to-hugo-exporter&quot;&gt;WP to Hugo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/plugins/jekyll-exporter/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Exporter&lt;/a&gt; migration tools, and perform both Exports. You’ll get two &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.zip&lt;/code&gt; files with a bunch of MarkDown in them. I’ve found that the Hugo version of the posts returns a better MarkDown conversion – but the files aren’t named as they should (i.e., prefixed with the date, like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2018-11-29-something.md&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jekyll-import&quot;&gt;Jekyll import&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have then manually reviewed the markdown files of the majority of my posts (~150) coming from the export, deleting items in the YAML FrontMatter&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:frontmatter&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:frontmatter&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that aren’t meaningful, and fixing the markdown.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure you keep the original &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;permalink&lt;/code&gt; (the post URL): this way each post will have the same URL of your old WP site. This way people who get to you from other sites’ links don’t get 404’ed, and you keep analytics intact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove in the MarkDown all the links to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://localhost:8888/&lt;/code&gt;. For instance, my Hugo export (the one with nicer markup) has all the posts’ assets with urls like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://localhost:8888/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/logo.png&lt;/code&gt;. Do a batch search and replace and turn them to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/logo.png&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move the markdown posts in Jekyll’s &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; folder, and also move in the website root the exported &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/wp-content&lt;/code&gt; folder, which contains all the images coming from WP&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:redundant&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:redundant&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of the YAML FrontMatter for this very post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot; data-lang=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Migrating from WordPress to Jekyll on Netlify&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;2019-03-05T11&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Davide Barranca&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;excerpt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Bye-bye Wordpress.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;permalink&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;/2019/03/migrating-from-wordpress-to-jekyll-on-netlify/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;description&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;How to migrate from WordPress to Jekyll on Netlify&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/jekyll.png&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;draft&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;category&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Personal&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;tags&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole idea around this SSG thing is that both the site build and the site updates must be easy. I’ve created a git repository on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and pushed my Jekyll website there. Be aware that GitHub itself provides you for free with &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, a service based on Jekyll that automatically builds your site each time you push a commit to a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch, and hosts the result on https for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some limitations in terms of Jekyll plugins (see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/en/articles/configuring-jekyll-plugins#default-plugins&quot;&gt;whitelist here&lt;/a&gt;), so I’ve decided to try a different approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;netlify&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go create a free account on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netlify.com/&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;, which provides an amazing service similar to GitHub pages. Then link your GitHub/Bitbucket repository, define a build command (mine is simply &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll build&lt;/code&gt;), and they will serve the Jekyll output on a dedicated, public subdomain – that you can use to check the site or point collaborators/clients to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you can link your existing domain (the process is quite easy): Netlify will give you few domain name servers to set e.g. on GoDaddy, or wherever your domain is hosted. You’ll be asked also to add to Netlify all the existing CNAME and MX records from your host (copy them from GoDaddy – they are for email, FTP and such).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you’ll have to wait some hours for the DNS propagation, during which your website won’be served through https – the free &lt;a href=&quot;https://letsencrypt.org/&quot;&gt;Let’s Encrypt&lt;/a&gt; certificate will be issued shortly, and your static site will finally be on SSL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/netlify.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hugo vs. Jekyll&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am genuinely happy to have streamlined my blogging workflow. There’s lot of room for improvement – e.g. on the theme, SEO, social cards etc. – but given the little time it took:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have gotten rid of WordPress and related expenses (pricey hosting and plugins).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Posts are easier to access, create and edit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I generally feel more in control, and less subject to random, time consuming issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I haven’t lost anything relevant in terms of functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had more time I’d explore Jekyll and Netlify features more in depth, or even consider adapting my theme to Hugo to save some building time in the future. Luckily, I haven’t got any spare time left 😅 So I’ll just call quit and feel good.&lt;br /&gt;
Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:template&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For a lack of better word. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:template&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:frontmatter&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s the &lt;em&gt;header&lt;/em&gt; content of each &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; file, which is wrapped with three dashes &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;---&lt;/code&gt;. It contains the post’s metadata (e.g. the title, the excerpt), that is used by Jekyll to display it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:frontmatter&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:redundant&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There is a lot of redundant stuff in there, for WP creates several versions of all images you’ve imported at different resolutions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:redundant&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/03/migrating-from-wordpress-to-jekyll-on-netlify/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/03/migrating-from-wordpress-to-jekyll-on-netlify/</guid>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        <category>Netlify</category>
        
        
        <category>Personal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adobe Extension Manager Error Codes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of Adobe Extension Manager &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ExManCmd&lt;/code&gt; error codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t use &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;zxp&lt;/code&gt; files to install my products, but some people do (e.g. with &lt;a href=&quot;https://install.anastasiy.com/&quot;&gt;Anastasiy’s Extension Manager&lt;/a&gt;, that under the hood calls &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ExManCmd&lt;/code&gt;) and error numbers are always hard to decode. The list has been kindly provided by Adobe’s Erin Finnegan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exmancmd-errors&quot;&gt;ExManCmd Errors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;EXMAN_FAILED_INSUFFICIENT_PRIVILEDGE = -151
EXMAN_FAILED_OPEN_FILES = -152
EXMAN_FAILED_READ_FILES = -154
EXMAN_FAILED_WRITE_FILES = -155
EXMAN_FAILED_COPY_FILES = -156
EXMAN_FAILED_DELETE_FILES = -157
EXMAN_FAILED_CREATE_FILES = -158
EXMAN_FAILED_FILE_TYPE_NOT_MATCH = -159
EXMAN_FAILED_FILE_NOT_FOUND = -160
EXMAN_FAILED_ITERATE_DIRECTORY = -161
EXMAN_FAILED_FILE_EXISTS_ALREADY = -162
EXMAN_FAILED_CHANGE_PERMISSION = -163
EXMAN_FAILED_CREATE_DIRECTORY = -164
EXMAN_FAILED_DIRECTORY_EXISTS_ALREADY = -165
EXMAN_FAILED_IS_NOT_DIRECTORY = -166
EXMAN_FAILED_IS_NOT_FILE = -167
EXMAN_FAILED_PATH_INVALID = -168
EXMAN_FAILED_PATH_NOT_FOUND = -169
EXMAN_FAILED_ACCESS_DENIED = -170
EXMAN_FAILED_FILE_LOCKED = -171
EXMAN_FAILED_SHARING_VIOLATION = -172
EXMAN_FAILED_JUDGE_FILE_EXIST = -173
EXMAN_FAILED_FILESCHEMA_ILLEGAL = -174
EXMAN_FAILED_ELEVATE_START = -175
EXMAN_FAILED_ELEVATE_FILEDEL = -176
EXMAN_FAILED_ELEVATE_FILECOPY = -178
EXMAN_FAILED_ELEVATE_MAKEDIR = -179
EXMAN_FAILED_UNHANDLED_EXCEPTION = -180
EXMAN_FAILED_NO_INSTALLED_FILES = -181
EXMAN_FAILED_ELEVATE_EXIST = -182
EXMAN_FAILED_IS_NOT_LINK = -183
EXMAN_FAILED_ELEVATE_ADDPERMISSION = -184
EXMAN_FAILED_EXTRACT_ZXP = -201
EXMAN_FAILED_DECRYPT = -202
EXMAN_FAILED_ENCRYPT = -203
EXMAN_FAILED_PARSE_XMANCONFIG = -251
EXMAN_FAILED_PARSE_MXI = -252
EXMAN_FAILED_DESTINATION_MISSING_TOKEN = -253
EXMAN_FAILED_PARENT_FOLDER_IN_PATH = -254
EXMAN_FAILED_SOURCE_FORMAT_ERROR = -255
EXMAN_FAILED_UNKNOWN_TOKEN = -256
EXMAN_FAILED_MANIFEST_NODE_NOT_FOUND = -257
EXMAN_FAILED_XML_NOT_FOUND = -259
EXMAN_FAILED_ELEMENT_NOT_FOUND = -260
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_VALUE_IN_MXI = -261
EXMAN_FAILED_OPEN_XMANCONFIG_URI = -262
EXMAN_FAILED_DOWNLOAD_XMANCONFIG = -263
EXMAN_FAILED_PARSE_TODOFILE = -264
EXMAN_FAILED_PARSE_XML = -265
EXMAN_FAILED_GENERATE_XMANCONFIG = -266
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_MANIFEST = -267
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_MANIFEST_VERSION = -268
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_MANIFEST_BUNDLE_ID = -269
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_MANIFEST_BUNDLE_VERSION = -270
EXMAN_FAILED_MANIFEST_EXCEPTION = -271
EXMAN_FAILED_RESOURCE_EXCEPTION = -272
EXMAN_FAILED_BLOCK_LIST_EXCEPTION = -273
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_BLOCK_LIST = -274
EXMAN_FAILED_CLOSE_HEADLIGHTS_SESSION = -302
EXMAN_FAILED_INIT_HEADLIGHTS = -303
EXMAN_FAILED_NULL_POINTER = -351
EXMAN_FAILED_BUFFER_NOT_ENOUGH = -352
EXMAN_FAILED_REJECT_LICENSE_AGREEMENT = -401
EXMAN_FAILED_SIGNATURE_VALIDATION = -402
EXMAN_FAILED_NO_PRODUCT_SUPPORT_THIS_CEP = -403
EXMAN_FAILED_CEP_NOT_SIGNED = -404
EXMAN_FAILED_REJECT_SIGNATURE_VALIDATION = -405
EXMAN_FAILED_EXTENSION_NOT_FOUND = -406
EXMAN_FAILED_REQUIRED_EXTENSION_NOT_INSTALLED = -407
EXMAN_FAILED_REQUIRED_EXTENSION_NOT_ENABLED = -408
EXMAN_FAILED_EXTENSION_BLOCKED = -409
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_ZXP_FILE = -410
EXMAN_FAILED_NO_SUPPORTED_PRODUCT = -411
EXMAN_FAILED_CONFLICT_EXTENSION_FOUND = -412
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_EMBEDDED_EXTENSION = -413
EXMAN_FAILED_EMBEDDED_EXTENSION_NOT_SIGNED = -414
EXMAN_FAILED_RESOURCE_FOLDER_NOT_FOUND = -415
EXMAN_FAILED_CREATE_EXTENSION = -416
EXMAN_FAILED_WRONGDEPENDENCY = -417
EXMAN_FAILED_NEWER_EXTENSION_INSTALLED = -418
EXMAN_FAILED_DEPENDENCY_CHANGED_WHEN_UPDATE = -419
EXMAN_FAILED_MXP_NO_SUPPORTED = -420
EXMAN_FAILED_DOWNLOAD_EXTENSION = -421
EXMAN_FAILED_REJECT_OVERWRITE_CONFLICT_EXTENSION = -422
EXMAN_FAILED_USER_CANCEL_DOWNLOAD = -423
EXMAN_FAILED_CAN_NOT_INSTALL_FOR_ALL = -424
EXMAN_FAILED_PRODUCT_NOT_FOUND = -451
EXMAN_FAILED_TOKEN_NOT_FOUND = -453
EXMAN_FAILED_PRODUCT_NOT_SUPPORTED = -454
EXMAN_FAILED_PARSER_PRODUCT_TOKEN = -455
EXMAN_FAILED_POINT_PRODUCT_NEED_QUIT = -456
EXMAN_FAILED_SPECIFIER_NOT_FOUND = -457
EXMAN_FAILED_REQUIRED_PRODUCT_NOT_INSTALLED = -458
EXMAN_FAILED_REQUIRED_VERSION_NOT_INSTALLED = -459
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_COMMON = -500
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_CONNECTFAILED = -501
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_DISCONNECTFAILED = -502
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_QUERYFAILED = -503
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_NOTSTARTUP = -504
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_NOTSHUTDOWN = -505
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_DATANOTFOUND = -506
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_CREATTABLFAILED = -507
EXMAN_FAILED_DBWRAPPER_NAME_EXIST = -508
EXMAN_FAILED_UPDATE_DATABASE = -509
EXMAN_FAILED_INIT_BT_FAILED = -552
EXMAN_FAILED_VALIDATE_LICENSE = -601
EXMAN_FAILED_GET_USER_ACOUNTDAT = -602
EXMAN_FAILED_INVALID_USERACOUNT = -603
EXMAN_FAILED_GET_LICENSE_CHECK_RESPONSE = -604
EXMAN_FAILED_COMMON_EXCEPTION = -651
EXMAN_FAILED_SSL_CONTEXT_EXCEPTION = -652
EXMAN_FAILED_SSL_EXCEPTION = -653
EXMAN_FAILED_COMMON_SET_MGMT = -851
EXMAN_FAILED_STRING_CONVERT = -901
EXMAN_FAILED_USER_NOT_FOUND = -902
EXMAN_FAILED_FETCH_USER_INFO = -903
EXMAN_FAILED_GET_USER_HOME_FOLDER = -904&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 11:04:05 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/adobe-extension-manager-error-codes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/02/adobe-extension-manager-error-codes/</guid>
        
        <category>Adobe Extension Manager</category>
        
        
        <category>CEP</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
